<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Military-Integration on Opinions</title>
    <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/tags/military-integration/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Military-Integration on Opinions</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/tags/military-integration/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The New Militarism</title>
      <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2025-12-05-the-new-militarism/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2025-12-05-the-new-militarism/</guid>
      <description>Cheated by the Americans - as always An old saying goes like this: &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t listen to what the Americans say, look at what the Americans do&amp;rdquo;
However, the ruling elites of European states never learned this wisdom.
The Cold War was a propaganda war and Europeans was brainwashed by that propaganda into believing what the Americans said could be trusted. So for the long post WWII era we have been living under the American security umbrella and not bothered much with military geopolitics - untill now.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 id="cheated-by-the-americans---as-always">Cheated by the Americans - as always</h1>
<p>An old saying goes like this: <em>&ldquo;Don&rsquo;t listen to what the Americans say,
look at what the Americans do&rdquo;</em></p>
<p>However, the ruling elites of European states never learned this wisdom.</p>
<p>The Cold War was a propaganda war and Europeans was brainwashed by that
propaganda into believing what the Americans said could be trusted.
So for the long post WWII era we have been living under the American
security umbrella and not bothered much with military geopolitics -
untill now.</p>
<p>Now the Americans has changed their sayings -
and the Euopean elites are shocked by what they hear -
a profound uncertainty is spreading about whether NATO can be trusted -
and a panic rush to <em>ReArm Europe</em> has started -
billions and billions of Euros are hastily mobilized (mostly by new debt!)
for military purposes - the goal being 5% of GDP.</p>
<h1 id="capitalism-at-work---as-always">Capitalism at work - as always</h1>
<p>Western Capitalism is stagnating and need a booster - and we have seen
it before: economic crises breeds wars.
(<em>It was not Keynes who brought us out of the depression - it was Schicklgruber</em>)</p>
<p>So now the American creates ambiguity and the Europeans&rsquo; fear raises the
money for economic expansion by military means - benefitting
mostly America&rsquo;s weapons industry.</p>
<h1 id="security-lock-in">Security lock-in</h1>
<p>But have a <a href="https://themindness.substack.com/p/weaponizing-time-part-iii-the-steel">closer look</a> and you will see that the Europeans are not developing
any souvereign security - but wading deeper and deeper into the sump of
American dependence and vassaldom.</p>
<p>What happens is that far from leaving Europe alone Washington is actively
integrating European capital into its own military-industrial base.
Driven by existential panic the US hegemon and the European ruling strata feed on each other in building
a <strong>world-wide integrated ecosystem of war</strong> in a desperate attempt to delay the inevitable arrival of a world they do not own anymore.
Europe is just providing the money and the war-theatre the Americans need.</p>
<p>We will all be collateral damage of our elites psychotic militarism.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
