<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Government on Opinions</title>
    <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/tags/government/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Government on Opinions</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/tags/government/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Liberalisms Blindness</title>
      <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2023-11-13-liberalisms-blindness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2023-11-13-liberalisms-blindness/</guid>
      <description>The Decline of America Anusar Farooqi (&amp;lsquo;Policy Tensor&amp;rsquo;) has provided an excellent discussion1 of how the decline of America come about and what can(?) be done to reverse it - and why Trump does not have the answers.
He does not discuss who have been responsible for the decline or whether it could have been omitted.
In my mind there is one culprit: liberalism.
Let me explain:
The Law of The Market Society Liberalism potently exploits egoism - calling for individual freedom (of enterprise) and forgetting the importance of collective values and equality of rights and endowments.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-decline-of-america">The Decline of America</h2>
<p>Anusar Farooqi (&lsquo;Policy Tensor&rsquo;) has provided an excellent <a href="https://policytensor.substack.com/p/notes-on-us-china-policy">discussion</a><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> of how the
<em>decline of America</em> come about and what can(?) be done to <em>reverse</em> it -
and why <em>Trump does not have the answers</em>.</p>
<p>He does not discuss <em>who have been responsible</em> for the decline or
whether it <em>could have been omitted</em>.</p>
<p>In my mind there is one culprit: <strong>liberalism</strong>.</p>
<p>Let me  explain:</p>
<h2 id="the-law-of-the-market-society">The Law of The Market Society</h2>
<p>Liberalism potently exploits egoism - calling for <em>individual freedom (of enterprise)</em>
and forgetting the importance of collective values and equality of rights
and endowments.</p>
<p>Over time growth excels at the costs of increasing inequality.
This if the law of the <em>market society</em>.</p>
<p>Not paying attention to this gradual rise of inequality is <strong>liberalism&rsquo;s blindness</strong>.</p>
<p>How can a society go on with such a blindness</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>for so many year?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>with so devasting consequences?</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="breeding-fascism">Breeding Fascism</h2>
<p>In the end it created a <em>monster</em> - the monster of <em>Donald Trump</em>.</p>
<p>But this is not the first time.
Liberalism has created monsters before: <em>fascism and Mussolini</em>,
<em>nazism  and Hitler</em> and a lot of other smaller ones.</p>
<p>So we knew the story: <em>liberalism over time breeds fascism</em>.
Trump is just the new brand for an old story.</p>
<p>Are the powerholders under a liberal era just <strong>blind</strong> or
do they see and <em>welcome the emerging fascism</em>?</p>
<p>Is it <em>fascism that emerges as a &lsquo;solution&rsquo;</em> to the problems
liberal capitalism itself creates?</p>
<h2 id="trump-will-only-make-things-worse">Trump will only make things worse</h2>
<p>Certainly a lot of Americans <em>now thinks Trump is a solution</em> -
as italians thought Mussolini was their solution and
germans thought Hitler was.</p>
<p>Farooqi rejetcs Trumps policy and thinks is will rather create
additional problems. In the end neither fascism or nazism
provided anything else than fake solutions - and catastrophes.</p>
<h2 id="governments-can-accelerate-liberalism-technology">Governments can accelerate liberalism (technology)</h2>
<p>But Farooqi stays on <em>within</em>  liberalism - his alternative
is rather <em>more of the same</em> although by governement
action -  not laissez faire.</p>
<p>His reasoning is briefly like this:</p>
<p>Much of the withering of the middle class is an effect of
the technology information &lsquo;revolution&rsquo;.
Managers can now control production processes with it-tools
without the need for a stratum of middlemen -
and also with fewer workers.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/rde/fig/us_job_quality_shift.png" type="" alt=""  /></p>
<p><em>Figure: Hollowing out The Middle -
Change in job growth by job quality.
US 1990-2010</em></p>
<p>The problem with liberalism is that is sees technological change
as an exogenous force - market and society just has to adapt.</p>
<p>However, this does not need to be so - &rsquo;technology is endogenous
to our institutional arrangements&rsquo; as Farooqi puts it.
Government can support some lines of technology and suppress others.
&lsquo;A carefully-designed technology policy ought to be one of the
pillars of open-ended American developmentalism&rsquo;.</p>
<p>Farooqi calls for a &lsquo;forced pace of the automation of all routine tasks&rsquo; -
reducing the numbers of deskilled jobs. Why?
&lsquo;Human workers are great bundles of skill.
Using them as automata is a poor use of their human capital.&rsquo;
This opens for reallocation of human capital towards more productive
activities.
&lsquo;Automation does not cause aggregate job losses.
Rather, automation reconfigures what tasks are
bundled together as jobs, increasing their creative content, reducing
drudgery, and making them more rewarding for workers.&rsquo;</p>
<p>It should be said that Farooqi&rsquo;s  context is the China-US confrontation.
His main worry is Trump&rsquo;s protectionism.
Rather he still thinks the US can anew outperform China,
if only the government steps in and give liberalism an extra push.</p>
<p>There are two pillars of accelerated liberalism:
upskilling the workforce and keep trade open.</p>
<p>It will be an long-term effort - aiming at
<strong>reskilling one hundred million Americans over the next decade</strong>,
&lsquo;constantly refining our strategy to upgrade the skill-set of the
American populace — for it is human capital that is the true
font of productivity&rsquo;.</p>
<p>In trade the US cannot prevent China from catching-up.
The only chance is for the US to &lsquo;run harder itself&rsquo;.</p>
<h2 id="rethinking-liberalism">Rethinking Liberalism</h2>
<p>Can this <em>accelerated liberalism on government support</em> really
save us from the <em>breeding fascism</em>?</p>
<p>I do not think so.</p>
<p>Number one: Somehow we are already &lsquo;overskilled&rsquo; - it shows
in the shrinking wage premium of college education.
There is no way for the whole majority to upskill  into the 1%.
Capitalism only gets more and more concentrated.</p>
<p>Number two: Keeping trade open will only increase the
process of capital concentration.
Liberalism has lost the globalization game due to it&rsquo;s <strong>blindness</strong>.</p>
<p>Today the setting is different:
There are other values than <em>entrepreneurial freedom and profit maximization</em>.
Liberalism has to take the back seat.
We need governments that aim for the collective health of the planet
and <em>scale down economic activity</em> for humankind to survive
it&rsquo;s own productivity.</p>
<p>The <em>breeding fascism</em> has to be countered by <em>redesigning society for
equality and collectivity,</em> not economic growth.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p><a href="https://policytensor.substack.com/p/notes-on-us-china-policy">https://policytensor.substack.com/p/notes-on-us-china-policy</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Krugmans Explanations</title>
      <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2018-01-25-krugmans-explanations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2018-01-25-krugmans-explanations/</guid>
      <description>Mainstream economics failure to &amp;lsquo;see the crisis coming&amp;rsquo; in 2008 is broadly regarded as a deficiency of the theory. However, Paul Krugman now argues that the theory was - and is - &amp;lsquo;good enough for government&amp;rsquo;. The failure of 2008 was not in the theory, but rather in deficient data collection. Macroeconomists &amp;ldquo;overlooked&amp;rdquo; the institutional changes in the financial sector and did not record appropriate data.
The &amp;ldquo;New Keynesians&amp;rdquo; - i.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mainstream economics failure to &lsquo;see the crisis coming&rsquo; in 2008
is broadly regarded as a deficiency of the theory.
However, Paul Krugman now argues that the theory was - and is - &lsquo;good
enough for government&rsquo;. The failure of 2008 was not in the theory,
but rather in deficient <em>data collection</em>. Macroeconomists &ldquo;overlooked&rdquo;
the institutional changes in the financial sector
and did not record appropriate data.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;New Keynesians&rdquo; - i.e. Krugman&rsquo;s &lsquo;Saltwater School&rsquo; based at
MIT and Harvard - took up the challenge by <em>dust[ing] off their old sticky-price models from the 1950s and 1960s, which told them three things:</em></p>
<ol>
<li>Very large budget deficits would not drive up near-zero interest rates.</li>
<li>Even large increases in the monetary base would not lead to high inflation, or even to corresponding increases in broader monetary aggregates.</li>
<li>There would be a positive national income multiplier, almost surely greater than one, from changes in government spending and taxation.</li>
</ol>
<p>Krugman argues that these propositions made the case for budget deficits in the aftermath of the collapse of 2008 which worked “remarkably well.”
This New Keynesian policy was a succes - in contrast to the more inflexible
responses promoted by the &lsquo;Freshwater - Chicago School&rsquo;.</p>
<p>However, fiscal expansion was soon replaced by austerity.</p>
<p>Krugman&rsquo;s version is not taken at face value by Robert Skidelsky who
argues that <em>when Keynes was briefly exhumed for six months in 2008-2009, it was for political, not intellectual, reasons. Because the New Keynesian models did not offer a sufficient basis for maintaining Keynesian policies once the economic emergency had been overcome, they were quickly abandoned.</em></p>
<p><em>The problem for New Keynesian macroeconomists is that they fail to acknowledge radical uncertainty in their models, leaving them without any theory of what to do in good times in order to avoid the bad times. Their focus on nominal wage and price rigidities implies that if these factors were absent, equilibrium would readily be achieved. They regard the financial sector as neutral, not as fundamental.</em></p>
<p><em>Without acknowledgement of uncertainty, saltwater economics is bound to collapse into its freshwater counterpart. New Keynesian “tweaking” will create limited political space for intervention, but not nearly enough to do a proper job. So Krugman’s argument, while provocative, is certainly not conclusive. Macroeconomics still needs to come up with a big new idea.</em></p>
<p><a href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/why-no-intellectual-shift-in-economics-by-robert-skidelsky-2018-01">Skidelsky</a></p>
<p><a href="https://academic.oup.com/oxrep/article/34/1-2/156/4781811">Krugman</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
