<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Sovereignty on Opinions</title>
    <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/tags/sovereignty/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sovereignty on Opinions</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/tags/sovereignty/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Donald makes it!</title>
      <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2025-03-13-donald-makes-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2025-03-13-donald-makes-it/</guid>
      <description>FINALLY - DONALD WILL MAKE IT!
Millions and millions of people have worked to destroy the American empire, and all of them failed. Now Donald is succeeding!
The neoliberal trade order since the late 80s was designed to destroy countries’ sovereignty, making it impossible to truly regulate investors, to run industrial policy, or even, in rich nations, to keep wages up. Donald puts an end to it!
Europeans always listened to America.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>FINALLY - DONALD WILL MAKE IT!</strong></p>
<p>Millions and millions of people have worked to destroy the American empire, and all of them failed. Now Donald is succeeding!</p>
<p>The neoliberal trade order since the late 80s was designed to destroy countries’ sovereignty, making it impossible to truly regulate investors, to run industrial policy, or even, in rich nations, to keep wages up. Donald puts an end to it!</p>
<p>Europeans always listened to America. Donald is forcing the Europeans to stop doing what America says.</p>
<p>This should have happened decades ago, and EU elites failure to man-up has cost Europe’s countries dearly.</p>
<p>The NATO should have been disbanded when the USSR fell.</p>
<p>The EU has been the neoliberal implementation engine in Europe, securing stagnation and de-industrialization, especially since the introduction of the Euro.
Donald speeds up the end of the American Empire, and the end of the “no industrial policy, no sovereignty” free trade order, and possibly the end of NATO and the American occupation of Europe.</p>
<p>For the first time since the US imposed its terrible neoliberal trade order on the world, there is at least a chance for most countries to be able to properly manage their own economic affairs.</p>
<p>Thanks Donald!</p>
<p>(adapted from <a href="https://www.ianwelsh.net/trump-is-the-best-president-of-my-life-unless-youre-american/">Welsh</a>)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
