<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Sometag on Opinions</title>
    <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/tags/sometag/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sometag on Opinions</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/tags/sometag/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Venezuela and Greenland</title>
      <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2026-01-07-venezuela-and-greenland/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2026-01-07-venezuela-and-greenland/</guid>
      <description>Low-Cost Imperialism has arrived The US has accumulated a national debt of $36 trillion and are facing a growing doubts about it capability to service it. Reduced trust will feed into increasing interest levels ahead and will just make the squeeze more severe. So why not go into &amp;lsquo;Viking Mode&amp;rsquo; - go out looting abroad for cheap real resources to balance the book!
When the goal is Resource Extraction, Democracy is an inefficiency.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="low-cost-imperialism-has-arrived">Low-Cost Imperialism has arrived</h2>
<p>The US has accumulated a national debt of $36 trillion
and are facing a growing doubts about it capability to service it.
Reduced trust will feed into increasing interest levels ahead
and will just make the squeeze more severe.
So why not go into &lsquo;Viking Mode&rsquo; -
go out looting abroad for cheap real resources to balance the book!</p>
<p>When the goal is Resource Extraction, Democracy is an inefficiency.
A puppet dictatorship is more streamlined.
Thus Rodrigues, not Machado in Venzuela -
and for Greenland we will have to wait to see.</p>
<h3 id="the-logic-behind-the-us-raid-on-venezuela">The Logic behind the US Raid on Venezuela</h3>
<p>The Shale Oil era did not bring US energy independence as many believes.
US shale fields produce “Light Tight Oil” (LTO) — thin as champagne.
This shale does not fit with the US Gulf Cooast Refineries, which are
set up for handling “Heavy Sour” crude.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
<p>This mismatch means refineries cannot efficiently produce diesel—the core fuel
that supports industrial logistics and suppresses inflation.
Venezuela’s Orinoco Belt is the world’s largest deposit of extra-heavy crude. For the US industrial system, Venezuela is not a sovereign nation; it is a “Physical Patch” that must be reclaimed.</p>
<p>Venezuela’s 300 billion barrels of proven reserves
constitute an asset package worth ~$24 trillion.
The US Military action is, in essence,
a “Hostile Takeover”: stripping assets from a “distressed debtor” and
injecting them into the ledgers of US energy giants to provide a physical
backstop for the Dollar’s credit for the next 20 years.</p>
<p>It is also to help the petrodollar system, established
by Henry Kissinger’s 1974 deal with Saudi Arabia requiring global oil sales
in USD, which creates artificial demand for the currency &amp; funds American
hegemony - but which has been in its death throes.</p>
<p>Venezuela is hit because it challenged the US by selling
oil in yuan, euros, rubles, bypassing the dollar,
&amp; building alternative payment channels with China.</p>
<p>The invasion counters accelerating global de-dollarization led by Russia,
China, Iran, and BRICS, as nations shift to non-dollar settlements and
alternatives to SWIFT.
But it signals desperation, potentially hastening the petrodollar’s decline.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></p>
<h3 id="the-logic-behind-the-us-raid-on-greenland">The Logic behind the US Raid on Greenland</h3>
<p>While the US go for resource hunt in Latin-America, China opens new
sea-routes in the Arctic.
The 2025 voyage of the Chinese-owned (Liberian flag), Panamax containership <em>Istanbul Bridge</em> signals a game-change for global maritime trade.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup></p>
<p>US maritime hegemony is built on absolute control of “Choke Points” (Malacca, Suez, Panama). These are the “valves” the US Navy can close at any time.</p>
<p>The new Arctic Route bypasses these Choke Points and
renders the US maritime defense system obsolete.</p>
<p>The US have to look for new options to regain maritime control -
and in the Artic Greenland is the closest they easily can come
at the moment.</p>
<p>As the Chinese artic route expands we can expect to see growing
American naval expansion in the Norwegian and Barents seas.</p>
<p>Apart for  these national security concerns of course the island of
Greenland will also be a resource grab, by itself, so better keep
the Chinese out from the beginning of the game.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p><a href="https://chinarbitrageur.substack.com/p/venezuela-and-the-arctic-two-ways">Chinarb</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p><a href="https://x.com/scientificecon/status/2007639806293987656">Werner</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p><a href="https://www.thebarentsobserver.com/opinion/arctic-voyage-of-the-containership-istanbul-bridge-and-the-imo-polar-code/439706">Barents Observer</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
